本视频由SurfShark赞助
This video is supported by SurfShark.
1967年11月 NASA的重型火箭土星五号首飞
In November 1967, NASA launched the iconic Saturn V rocket for the first time.
110米高 起飞推力760万磅(3400+吨)
Standing 110 meters tall and producing 7.6 million pounds of thrust,
让土星五号仍是至今最大 推力最强的火箭
the Saturn V stillI holds the record for the largest and most powerful rocket ever launched.
但在土星五号之前 人类设计的一款火箭将直接碾压它的大小
But a rocket designed years before the Saturn V would have shattered the scale of rocket design
并彻底改变火箭科技的走向
and altered the course of rocket technology.
这款火箭就是海龙号
The rocket was known as the Sea Dragon.
这是一款巨大的两级火箭 设计定位低成本 发射超重载荷入轨
This was an enormous two staged rocket, aiming to cut costs and launch extremely heavy payloads into space.
海龙号的想法初见于六十年代早期的工程师Robert Truax脑中
The idea for the Sea Dragon came from engineer Robert Truax in the early 60's.
Truax考虑的是一款两级半可复用火箭
Truax envisioned a semi-reusable two-stage launch vehicle,
可以将大量载荷送往月球和火星
capable of delivering extreme payloads to the Moon and Mars.
火箭设计的背后处处体现着对于结构简单 可复用 低成本的追求
Simplicity, reusability, and cost-savings were the guiding principles behind the rocket's design.
海龙号的一级只有一台发动机 而不是土星五号那样的多发并联
Sea Dragon's first stage consisted of a single engine rather than multiple smaller engines like the Saturn V.
发动机没有使用复杂的燃料泵
Instead of using complex fuel pumps,
而是使用液氮储箱为燃料箱加压 将燃料挤压进发动机
it had liquid nitrogen tanks which would pressurize the fuel tanks and push the propellants into the engine.
这样燃料泵复杂且不可靠的因素就没有了
Taking away the complex and unreliable fuel pumps
使得发动机制造成本低 易于维护
would make the engine cheaper to build and easier to refurbish.
而火箭的两级设计都是可翻新后复用的
Since both stages of the rocket were designed to be refurbished and reused,
所以它们每次发射后的回收都要小心谨慎
they had to be recovered carefully after each launch.
火箭发射后达到38公里高空时
Once the rocket launched and reached an altitude of about 38 kilometers,
一级发动机关机 之后一二级分离
the first stage engine would cut out and separate from the 2nd stage.
然后在落回地球的过程中展开喇叭形的伞
It would continue to fall back to Earth using an inflatable flare.
这一方面可以使它减速
This would help to slow the stage down
另一方面还能调整好落水姿态 防止损伤发动机
and orientate it in a way that wouldn't damage the engine once it hit the ocean.
二级在将载荷送入轨道后也会以类似的方式返回地球
The second stage would follow a similar path back to Earth after delivering the payload into orbit.
由于海龙号的体型过于庞大 地面建造+陆路运输是不可能的了
Given the sheer size of the Sea Dragon, it would have been far too big to build and transport on land.
起飞时巨大无比的噪声也会产生足以摧毁火箭自身和发射台的冲击波
The incredible amount of sound generated during liftoff
would have created shockwaves strong enough to damage the launch pad and the rocket itself.
为了解决这些问题 火箭需要直接在海上建造并发射
In order to overcome these issues, the rocket would need to be built and launched at sea.
火箭会在船坞内制造 之后拖到发射场
The rocket would be built in a shipyard and towed out to the launch site.
为了让火箭竖起来
In order to orient the rocket vertically,
火箭底部的六个储箱会注满水 让发动机沉入海中
6 tanks near the base of the rocket would fill with water and sink the engine into the sea.
虽然海射火箭在二战中就有所应用
Although sea-launched rockets had already been used during the second World War,
但类似技术还从未在如此巨大的火箭上应用过
the technology had never been tested on such an enormous scale.
为了测试海龙号火箭
In order to begin testing the Sea Dragon,
工程师将美国海军的“海马火箭”进行了改装
engineers modified a rocket from the U.S. Navy nicknamed 'Sea Horse'.
测试开始于旧金山湾 工程师们将发动机在水上点火 之后沉入水中
Testing began in San Francisco Bay where engineers fired the rocket's engine
on a barge above the water and slowly lowered it into the water.
他们发现发动机入水后仍能稳定燃烧
The engineers found that once submerged, the engine continued to fire perfectly
且海水会大大减少冲击波
and the sea dampened the shockwaves substantially.
这次测试的成功让海龙号离诞生更进一步
The success of this test opened the door for the Sea Dragon to become a reality.
然而就像很多其他火箭一样 海龙号最终还是停留在了图纸阶段
However, like many other rocket designs, Sea Dragon failed to leave the drawing boards.
六十年代晚期
As the 1960's came to a close,
美国投身越战 NASA的预算大幅缩减
NASA's budget was slashed as the United States went to war with Vietnam.
译注：1966年的59亿相当于2020年的476亿左右
在六十年代里 NASA年度预算顶峰达到了59亿美元
At the height of the decade, NASA's annual budget peaked at $5.9 billion.
随后几年 预算减少了37%
Over the next few years, their budget was reduced by 37%.
预算的削减导致NASA大量实验性研究工程被叫停
These cuts ended many of NASA's experimental research programs
当中就有海龙号的建造工作
along with the construction of the Sea Dragon.
各方面来讲 海龙号的巨大体型导致了它的夭折
In many ways, the sheer size of the rocket's design contributed to the downfall of Sea Dragon.
随着土星五号火箭研发的继续
As the Saturn V rocket continued to develop,
NASA正从拥有更大 推力更强的火箭中获益
NASA were reaping the benefits of having a rocket much larger
and more powerful than anything else that had come before.
虽然海龙号可能为发射更大载荷提供新的思路
Although Sea Dragon would have opened the door for even larger payloads,
但NASA却无法权衡制造海龙号时研发未验证技术所需的成本
NASA couldn't justify the cost of developing the unproven technology required to make Sea Dragon operational.
从技术角度来看 这种尺度的火箭还会有燃烧不稳定的担忧
From a technical standpoint, there were also concerns with combustion instability for a rocket this large.
海龙号起飞推力超过7900万磅（35800吨）
Sea Dragon would have generated more than 79 million pounds of thrust at liftoff,
大概是土星五号的十倍——而土星五号就遇到过燃烧不稳定的问题
10 times the amount of the Saturn V - which had its own combustion instability problems.
无论如何 这款曾经几乎呼之欲出的 概念极其疯狂的火箭 还是退出了历史舞台
Either way, the Sea Dragon will go down in history as one of the craziest rocket concepts that almost happened.
1973年土星五号退役后
Since the retirement of the Saturn V in 1973,
太空叉的Starship算是目前最接近海龙号概念的火箭了
SpaceX's Starship rocket is the closest thing we have to the Sea Dragon concept.
Starship设计高度118米 推力16万磅（7200吨）
Starship is designed to be 118 meter tall and produce 16 million pounds of thrust.
虽然我们没看到充满野心的海龙号
So although we never got to see what became of the incredibly ambitious Sea Dragon,
但我们还是可以期待一下世界航天的令人兴奋的未来
we can look forward to the exciting future that lies ahead in the world of spaceflight.
感谢SurfShark赞助本期Primal Space视频
Thanks to SurfShark for supporting this episode of Primal Space.
对于平常经常上网的人来说 VPN是不可或缺的
As someone who consumes an enormous amount of online content, having a VPN is essential.
使用VPN之前 我经常会遇到某些视频在我的国家不可用
Before using a VPN, I was always coming across videos that were blocked in my country.
有了SurfShark 你可以轻松更换自己的服务器所在国家
With SurfShark, you can easily change which country and server you want to connect to,
让你完全的自由！
giving you total freedom!
而SurfShark的主要目的是保护你的上网隐私
But SurfShark's main purpose is protecting your online privacy.
SurfShark会为你的个人信息加密 并隐藏你的IP地址
SurfShark encrypts all of your personal information and hides your IP address
无论你在上网看什么猎奇玩意 都没人能知道
so nobody can see what you're doing online, no matter how weird it is!
SurfShark也是目前唯一可以在多设备同时使用的VPN
SurfShark is also the only VPN that can be used on multiple devices simultaneously.
如果你想支持本频道 并想自由上网的话 欢迎访问SurfShark.deals/primalspace
To support this channel and get total internet freedom, visit SurfShark.deals/primalspace
使用代码PRIMALSPACE可以获取83%的优惠
and use the code 'PRIMALSPACE' to get 83% off when you sign up.
同时还会送你额外一个月的免费使用期 简直是最合算的VPN了！
On top of that, you'll get an extra month for free - making this the most affordable VPN around!
感谢观看本期视频 我们下期视频见！
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video!